Finding Aid for Merit Network, Inc. Records, 1966-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Networks
  - NSFNET
    - Events/Occasions
      - Seminars
        - Networking/Internetworking seminar
          - 1989-1992, 4 folders (Box 30)
        - Technical seminar 1990 (Box 30)
    - Press/Publicity
      - Information services 1989-1990 (Box 31)
        (3 bound volumes)
      - Marketing material (Box 31)
      - News clippings 1987-1989, 2 folders (Box 31)
      - NSFNET in the news (Box 31)
      - NSFNET National Net '90, promotional materials, press clippings 1990 (Box 31)
      - Press breakfast, Washington D.C. 1988 (Box 31)
      - Press clippings
        - 1987-1990 (Box 31)
        - 1991-1994 (Box 31)
      - Press conference November 1987 (Box 31)
      - Press releases 1989-1994 (Box 31)
      - Print publication clips 1990 (Box 32)
        (2 binders)
    - Proposals/Projects
      - ANS: router configuration generation 1995-1996 (Box 32)
      - CA*net 1990-1993 (Box 32)
      - Coordinated routing for the NSFNET 1986-1989 (Box 32)
      - DARPA/NASA extension 1992-1994 (Box 32)
      - Fox II 1992-1993 (Box 32)
      - International connections 1990 (Box 32)
      - International routing 1992 (Box 32)
      - Internet2 (i2) 1997-1998 (Box 32)
      - Internet assisted instruction 1993 (Box 32)
      - MAE EAST/SNAP WEST 1993 (Box 32)
      - MBONE 1994-1996 (Box 32)
      - Network Information Service Managers (NIS) 1992 (Box 33)
        - General (Box 33)
        - Solicitation (Box 33)
        - Proposal (Box 33)
        - Budget (Box 33)
        - Questions on solicitation and response retreats (Box 33)
      - National Research and Education Network (NREN) 1989-1992 (Box 33)
      - NSF -- Rover 1992 (Box 33)
      - Phillips/Sanda extension 1993-1995
        - Correspondence (Box 33)
        - Official documents (Box 33)
      - Research Interagency Backbone (RIB) 1989 (Box 33)
      - Sprint Mail Gateway 1993 (Box 33)
      - University Satellite Network (USAN)
        - Contracts
          - 1985 (Box 33)
          - 1987-1988 (Box 33)
        - Documents (Box 33)
        - FCC form 430 (Box 33)
        - Meetings and agendas (Box 33)
        - Quarterly reports (Box 33)
        - Technical proposal (Box 33)
        - Vitalink documents (Box 33)
      - WATS -- asynchronous access to NSFNET 1988-1990 (Box 34)
    - Reports
      - Annual reports 1988-1994, 2 folders (Box 34)
      - Final report and project personnel for network infrastructure 1995 (Box 34)
      - Hearing on management of NSFNET 1992 (Box 34)
      - Letters of transmittal 1988-1995 (Box 34)
      - Monthly reports July 1988-April 1995, 3 folders (Box 34)
      - Performance reports, 1990-91 (Box 35)
      - Program review 1989 (Box 35)
      - Quarterly reports 1988-1995 (Box 35)
      - Review of NSFNET 1993, 2 folders (Box 35)
    - Advanced Network & Services, Inc. (ANS)/Valuga
      - Valuga
        - 1990
          - January-September, 6 folders (Box 36)
      - ANS
        - 1990
          - September-December, 4 folders (Box 36)
        - 1991, 7 folders (Box 37)
        - 1992
          - January-June, 2 folders (Box 37)
          - July-September (Box 37)
        - 1993, 2 folders (Box 38)
        - 1994, 2 folders (Box 38)
        - 1995 (Box 38)
        - Announcement September 17, 1990 (Box 38)
        - MAE-east & AUP issues 1992-1993 (Box 38)
        - National Science Foundation (NSF)
          - ANS/Merit original contracts 1990 (Box 38)
          - ANS established as a non-profit 1990 (Box 38)
          - ANSnet services agreement 1991-1992 (Box 38)
          - Merit response to NSF 1992 (Box 38)
          - OIG NSFNET report (Box 38)
            (ANS comments)
          - ANS relationship (Box 38)
          - ANS -- lease (Box 38)
        - Phase IV 1992 (Box 38)
        - Regional agreements 1992 (Box 38)
        - Subcontract
          - Amended 1991 (Box 38)
          - Amended 1993 (Box 38)
          - Amended 1994 (Box 38)
          - Draft rebid 1993 (Box 38)
      - ANS/ANS CO+RE
        - Connectivity agreement 1991 (Box 38)
        - T3 gateway attachment agreement 1992-1993 (Box 38)
        - Cooperative marketing agreement 1992 (Box 38)
        - Strategic partnership plan 1992 (Box 38)
        - Resource Allocation Committee (RAC)
          - 1993-1996, 4 folders (Box 38)
    - CICNET
      - 1988, 3 folders (Box 39)
      - 1989, 4 folders (Box 39)
      - 1990, 4 folders (Box 39)
      - 1991 (Box 40)
        - General (Box 40)
        - Board meeting (Box 40)
      - 1992 (Box 40)
      - 1993
        - General (Box 40)
        - Rural datafication (Box 40)
      - 1994-1997, 4 folders (Box 40)
      - Agreement drafts 1988-1989 (Box 40)
      - Agreement 1989-1991 (Box 40)
      - Equipment selection 1988-1990 (Box 40)
      - ITD:CICMGMT 1986-1990 (Box 40)
      - Review 1990 (Box 40)
      - Site notebook 1990 (Box 40)
    - FARNET
      - 1986-1989, 3 folders (Box 41)
      - 1990
        - General (Box 41)
        - Meetings, 2 folders (Box 41)
      - 1991
        - General (Box 41)
        - Meetings, 3 folders (Box 41)
      - 1992
        - General (Box 41)
        - Meetings, 2 folders (Box 41)
      - 1993
        - General (Box 42)
        - Meetings, 2 folders (Box 42)
      - 1994
        - General (Box 42)
        - Meetings, 3 folders (Box 42)
      - 1995
        - General, 5 folders (Box 42)
        - Meetings, 4 folders (Box 42)
      - 1996
        - General, 4 folders (Box 42)
        - Meetings, 3 folders (Box 42)
        - FARNET elections (Box 42)
      - 1997
        - General, 4 folders (Box 43)
        - Meetings, 2 folders (Box 43)
      - 1998, 4 folders (Box 43)
    - Routing Arbiter
      - 1995
        - May-December, 8 folders (Box 43)
      - 1996
        - January-April, 4 folders (Box 43)
        - May-December, 8 folders (Box 44)
        - NAP/RA review July 1996 (Box 44)
      - 1997, 12 folders (Box 44)
      - 1998, 4 folders (Box 44)
      - 1999, 2 folders (Box 44)
      - Implementation correspondence
        - October 1994-July 1995, September 1995, 10 folders (Box 45)
      - NSF
        - 9352-ISI/USC/IBM 1994 (Box 45)
        - Negotiations 1992-1994 (Box 45)
        - Protests 1992-1994 (Box 45)
        - Response to draft solicitation 1992 (Box 45)
        - Routing arbiter review 1996-1997 (Box 45)
      - Net management 1994-1995 (Box 45)
      - Projects
        - Asynchronous transfer mode 1994 (Box 45)
      - Proposals and reports 1995-1998 (Box 45)
      - Recompete
        - Bellcore 1993 (Box 45)
        - Metropolitan Fiber Systems (MFS) 1992-1993 (Box 45)
        - Sprint 1993 (Box 45)
      - Reports 1995-1996 (Box 45)
      - Service at NASA (Box 45)
- Staff Files
  The Staff Files (8 linear ft., 1984-2000) contains the files of Eric Aupperle and Elise Gerich. Eric Aupperle headed Merit from 1974-2001. His files consist mainly of NSFNET correspondence (arranged chronologically) and other administrative documents. The files of Elise Gerich, Manager of Internet Engineers, contains mostly NSFNET-related files on the transition, T1 and T3 upgrades, and the routing arbiter. Some of her materials include presentations.
  - Eric Aupperle
    - ARPA/Fuzzball
      - General 1981-1989 (Box 46)
      - External network application forms and policy 1985 (Box 46)
    - Defense Data Network. Internet 1985 (Box 46)
    - Internet engineering
      - General (Box 46)
      - 1990-2000, 13 folders (Box 46)
    - NSFNET
      - 1984-1986 (Box 46)
      - 1988, 10 folders (Box 47)
      - 1989
        - January-June, 5 folders (Box 47)
        - July-December, 4 folders (Box 48)
      - 1990, 4 folders (Box 48)
      - 1991
        - January-April, 2 folders (Box 48)
        - May-December, 8 folders (Box 49)
      - 1992
        - January-June, 6 folders (Box 49)
        - July-December, 6 folders (Box 50)
      - 1993 (Box 50)
      - 1994, 12 folders (Box 51)
      - 1995
        - January-June, 5 folders (Box 51)
        - September-December, 2 folders (Box 52)
      - 1996
        - January-March (Box 52)
        - July-September (Box 52)
      - Extension proposal 1992 (Box 52)
      - Recompete 1992-1993, 2 folders (Box 52)
      - Research Interagency Backbone (RIB)
        - "Sanitized proposal," 1988 (Box 52)
        - Overheads 1988 (Box 52)
        - Draft and working notes 1988 (Box 52)
        - Solicitation 1989 (Box 52)
        - Expansion proposal 1989 (Box 52)
  - Elise Gerich
    - Accomplishments and statistics 1995 (Box 53)
    - Executive Committee meeting 1992 (Box 53)
    - FNC-NREN directives 1989-1990 (Box 53)
    - International Connections Management (ICM) award 1990 (Box 53)
    - IP register presentation 1991 (Box 53)
    - NSFNET 1988-1991 (Box 53)
    - NSFNET Executive Committee Meeting 1992 (Box 53)
    - Presentation (Blois) 1991 (Box 53)
    - Proposal to NSF (revised NASA proposal) 1993 (Box 53)
    - Routing arbiter 1993-1995, 2 folders (Box 53)
    - T1 questionnaire (Box 53)
    - T3 June 1990, 3 folders (Box 53)
    - Transition 1994-1995
      - General (Box 53)
      - 1994 (Box 53)
      - 1995 (Box 53)
    - Update meeting minutes 1988-1989 (Box 53)
- Audiovisual
  The Audiovisual materials (3 linear ft., 1980-1990) include videotapes (U-matic, SVHS and 1" film reels), audiotapes, and slides. The audiovisual materials appear to cover seminars and workshops, Merit background and history, and seminars and presentations.
  - Audio
    - Merit -- Regional Network Consortium, (2 cassette tapes (Box 54)
    - Unlabeled, (2 cassette tapes (Box 54)
  - Video
    - 0.5" video
      - Woman at workstation-promotional tape? (Box 54)
    - 1" magnetic tapes
      - Tape list (Box 54)
      - MSTAT A (Box 54)
      - MSTAT B (Box 54)
      - UMSTAT 6 (Box 54)
      - Unlabeled, (3 tapes (Box 54)
    - U-matic videotapes
      - Merit Computer network-Community of users 1973 (Box 54)
      - Unlabeled, (3 videotapes (Box 54)
    - SVHS
      - Susan Hares, EGP January 23, 1980 (Box 55)
      - Elise, Sue, Cathy, Routing trouble shoot February 1988 (Box 55)
      - Dave Katz, Merit, FDDI January 9, 1989 (Box 55)
      - NSFNET internal training presentation-Cathy Aronson, CICNet overview February 1989 (Box 55)
      - Steve Gold, NOC hardware-software overview February 21, 1989 (Box 55)
      - Advanced NSFNET workshop March 8-9, 1989, (6 videotapes (Box 55)
      - "Connecting to the rest of the world," July 1989, (6 videotapes (Box 55)
      - Advanced topics seminar August 1989, (5 videotapes (Box 55)
      - Jim Sweeton, OSI layers September 12, 1989, (3 videotapes (Box 55)
      - Dory Lieffer, ISDN November 14, 1989 (Box 55)
      - Mark Knopper, Merit re-configuration November 21, 1989 (Box 55)
      - 802.6 MIRV November 28, 1989 (Box 55)
      - Bert's Merit equipment talk December 7, 1989 (Box 55)
      - Kraig Meyer, Domain name system (DNS) basics December 21, 1989 (Box 55)
      - Tom Libert on UNIX, December 7 and December 12 (Box 55)
        (year unknown)
      - Bryan, Beecher talk, DNS, December 14 (Box 55)
      - Randy Frank, "EECS 489: Computer Networks & Protocols" January-April 1990, (20 videotapes (Box 56)
        (tape number 10 missing)
      - Fred Resnely February 13, 1990 (Box 56)
      - CICNET-CJA February 22, 1990 (Box 56)
      - CJA-CICNET March 1, 1990 (Box 56)
      - Tom Libert, parts III and IV March 1990, (2 videotapes (Box 56)
      - Road Show undated, (6 videotapes (Box 56)
      - Tom Libert, Intro to Binary Logic, Channel 4 news: Friday the 13th virus undated (Box 56)
    - Visual
      - Binder of presentation slides (Box 56)
      - Various slides of computers, computer users on campus, and presentations (Box 56)
- Publications
  The Publications series (3.5 linear ft., 1970-1994) includes Merit-produced publications, like newsletters and technical documentation as well as publications authored by Eric Aupperle relating to computers and networking. Of special note are packets of materials (readings and other information) that Aupperle compiled for short intensive summer courses he taught on computing and networking in the College of Engineering at the University of Michigan.
  - Eric Aupperle
    - Intensive summer short course, College of Engineering, University of Michigan
      - July 27-31, 1970 Minicomputers: their structure, characteristics and applications (Box 57)
      - July 26-30, 1971 Minicomputers: their structure, characteristics and applications (Box 57)
      - June 26-30, 1972 Advanced electronic instrumentation for Engineers (Box 57)
      - July 24-28, 1972 Minicomputers: their structure, characteristics and applications (Box 57)
      - July 11-13, 1973 Introduction to computer networking (Box 57)
      - July 30-August 3, 1973 Minicomputers: their structure, characteristics and applications (Box 57)
      - July 29-August 2, 1974 Minicomputers: their structure, characteristics and applications (Box 57)
      - July 28-August 1, 1975 Mini and microcomputers: their structures, characteristics, and applications (Box 57)
      - July 26-30, 1976 Mini and microcomputers: their structures, characteristics, and applications (Box 57)
      - July 23-27, 1979 Mini and microcomputers: their structures, characteristics, and applications (Box 57)
      - July 21-25, 1980 Mini and microcomputers: their structures, characteristics, and applications (Box 58)
      - July 28-August 1, 1980 Microcomputer system design and applications (Box 58)
      - July 20-24, 1981 Mini and microcomputers: their structures, characteristics, and applications (Box 58)
      - July 27-31, 1981 Microcomputer system design and applications (Box 58)
    - Industrial Sciences Group, College of Engineering, University of Michigan
      - An alphanumeric display terminal with abundant memory September 1967 (Box 58)
      - Bryan visual display system November 1969 (Box 58)
      - Phase-lock tracking system May 1970 (Box 58)
    - Miscellaneous publications
      - Impact of minicomputers on research and manufacturing 1969 (Box 58)
      - A tutorial on computer communications and networks 1970s (Box 58)
  - Merit publications
    - List of Merit publications August 1977 (Box 59)
    - 1970
      - Merit proposal summary, February 1970 (Box 59)
      - Link editor user's guide, August 1970 (Box 59)
        (0870-UM-1)
      - The MAL user's guide, August 1970 (Box 59)
        (0870-UM-2)
      - The communications computer operating system--the initial design, October 1970 (Box 59)
        (1070-TN-3)
    - 1971
      - A representative sample of facilities and activities at the University of Michigan bearing on instructional uses of computing, March 1971 (Box 59)
      - Progress report, July 1969-March 1971, May 1971 (Box 59)
        (0571-PR-4)
      - Program logic manual for MAL, July 1971 (Box 59)
        (0771-TR-6)
      - MAL user's guide and LINK11 user's guide, July 1971 (Box 59)
        (MCN-0771-UM-5)
      - Progress on applications development, 1970-1971 A report of the Associate Directors of MERIT, December 1971 (Box 59)
        (MCN-1271-PR-7)
    - 1972
      - Computer networks, May 1972 (Box 59)
        (MCN-0572-TP-8)
      - The communications computer hardware of the Merit computer network, June 1972 (Box 59)
        (MCN-0672-TP-9)
      - Computers and education at Wayne State University, October 1972 (Box 59)
        (MCN-1072-GE-10)
    - 1973
      - Organizational issues and the computer network market, February 1973 (MCN-0273-TP-12) (Box 59)
      - The Merit network re-examined, February 1973 (Box 59)
        (MCN-0273-TP-13)
      - User's guide (preliminary), April 1973 (Box 59)
        (MCN-0473-UM-11)
      - Facilities & resources available via the Merit host computing centers, May 1973 (Box 59)
        (MCN-0573-GE-14)
      - Progress on applications development, 1971-73: a report of the Associate Directors of MERIT, fall 1973 (Box 59)
        (MCN-1173-PR-15)
    - 1974
      - Educational computing at the University of Michigan a survey of activities and resources September 1974
        (MCN-0874-GE-16)
        - Draft April 1974 (Box 59)
        - Addendum February 1975 (Box 59)
      - User's guide, September 1974 (Box 59)
        (MCN-0974-UM-17)
      - Load sharing in computer networks: a queueing model November 1974 (Box 59)
    - 1975
      - A theoretical study of store-and-forward message switching the Merit computer network, June 1975 (Box 59)
        (MCN-0675-TP-19)
      - Merit computer network experiences, July 1975 (Box 59)
        (MCN-0775-TP-20)
      - User's guide, August 1975 (Box 59)
        (MCN-0875-UM-21)
    - 1976
      - Message-switching protocols in distributed computer networks, July 1976 (Box 59)
        (MCN-0776-TR-22)
    - 1977
      - Educational computing at the University of Michigan: a survey of activities and resources, 1976-77, June 1977 (Box 59)
        (MCN-0677-GE-17)
    - 1980
      - Merit's evolution--statistically speaking, January 1980 (Box 59)
        (MCN-0180-T P-24)
    - 1985
      - Computer network offers a host of opportunities, in The Research News, vol.36, no.3-4, March /April 1985 (Box 59)
    - 1991
      - Getting started with networking: using the internet, September 1991 (Box 59)
    - 1992
      - Navigating the internet: a hands-on tutorial of networking information delivery tools, October 1992 (Box 59)
  - Newsletters
    - Link letter 1988-1994 (Box 60)
    - Merit network news, 1986, 1989 (Box 60)
    - Merit news section of Computing Center Newsletter, 1975-1979 (Box 60)
    - Michnet news, 1990-1991, 1995-1997 (Box 60)
    - NSF network news, 1987-1994 (Box 60)
    - On-line, 1972-1977 (Box 60)
Related Material
Other collections at the Bentley Historical Library contain Merit material. Short descriptions of Merit-related material in these collections can be found below:
Information Technology Division (University of Michigan) records
The Networks series (4 linear ft., 1984-1992) documents the university's and ITD's participation in a number of local, regional, and national computer networking organizations, including Bitnet, CICNet (Committee on Institutional Cooperation Network), CREN (Corporation for Research and Educational Networking), Merit, MITN (Michigan Information Technology Network), NREN (National Research and Educational Network), NSFNET (National Science Foundation Network), and ONENET. The material reflects the university's participation as member, host, or manager and/or Van Houweling's service as a board member or advisor.
The Merit, NSFNet, and CICNet records are the most significant. Since Merit managed the NSFNET network, researchers should note that the Merit files hold considerable material on NSFNET. Other records include Board of Directors minutes, correspondence, and a topical file. Of particular note in the topical file are drafts entitled "Merit: Michigan Universities Computer Network" and an unpublished paper on the history of Merit, 1989. There are also copies of the agreements among UM, NSF and Merit, including several grant proposals. (Note: This is not the archives of Merit, but only material collected by Van Houweling in his role as chairman of the board.) The NSFNet files include executive committee minutes and correspondence, quarterly and annual reports on the operation of the network, and speeches by Van Houweling about NSFNet. The CICNet material is comprised of a single chronological file of correspondence, minutes and reports.
Computing Center (University of Michigan) records
The Merit Network series (1 linear ft., 1978-1989) includes eight folders of board of director and director advisory committee correspondence, minutes and agendas for 1979 to 1989; NSF (National Science Foundation) proposals, correspondence and background for 1986-1988; and miscellaneous organizational files. Researchers will find more extensive material about Michigan's Merit network, its management and re-engineering of the NSFNET backbone service (a collaboration with IBM and MCI) and further description of the evolution of the Internet which it helped pioneer, in the Information Technology Division (ITD) record group.
Material at the Bentley Historical Library related to computing at the University of Michigan includes the following:
University Committee on Computer Policy and Utilization records
Logic of Computers Group records
Inter-University Consortium for Political and Social Research records
Arthur W. Burks papers
Bernard Galler papers
Aaron Finerman papers
Karl Zinn papers
Bibliography
For more extensive background and historical material on Merit and NSFNET, researchers may find the following resources useful:
"A Chronicle of Merit's Early History" and "Merit - Who, What, and Why"
"NSFNET Final Report" (PDF) available at: http://www.merit.edu/home/about/history.html
Online versions of the Link Letter, a publication of Merit/NSFNET can be found at: http://www.funet.fi/pub/netinfo/NSFNET/Linkletter/